<refentry xmlns:p="http://www.w3.org/ns/xproc"
          xmlns:e="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Spec/ElementSyntax"
          xmlns:cxerr="http://xmlcalabash.com/ns/error"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xml:id="cx-trang">
<?db filename="cx-trang"?>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>cx:trang</refname>
  <refpurpose>Convert between schema formats</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<refsection role="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>This step converts between DTD, RELAX NG, and XML Schema grammar formats
with <link xlink:href="https://relaxng.org/jclark/trang.html">Trang</link>.
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection role="step-declaration">
<title>Step declaration</title>
<xi:include href="../../../../ext/trang/src/main/resources/com/xmlcalabash/ext/trang.xpl"
            xpointer="xpath(/*/*[@type='cx:trang'])"/>
<?import trang.xpl?>
</refsection>

<refsection role="errors">
<title>Errors</title>
<para>Errors from the entry body are summarized here.</para>
</refsection>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>Trang translates between DTD, RELAX NG, and XML Schema grammar formats. At
least one schema must be provided on the <port>source</port> port. <error
code="cxerr:XC0025">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if no schemas
are provided.</error></para>

<para>The underlying Trang APIs are really designed to operate on files. Making
them work with a sequence of dynamically provided schemas requires a little
effort. For a single schema document, with no references to other schema
documents, the conversion is straightforward. For a set of schema documents that contain
cross-references (parameters entities in DTDs or RELAX NG include elements), it’s
a bit more complicated.</para>

<para>For a set of related schemas, you must provide all of the schemas on the
<port>source</port> port, and they must all have base URIs and those URIs must
use the file: URI scheme.
<error code="cxerr:XC0029">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if multiple
schemas are provided and they do not all have base URIs.</error>
<error code="cxerr:XC0030">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any schema
document has a base URI that is not a file: URI.</error>
If the
cross-references use relative URIs, then they will be resolved against the base
URI of the document in which they appear. Every resolved base URI must be the same
as the base URI of one of the input schemas.
<error code="cxerr:XC0035">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if any reference
is made to a schema document that has a URI not among the source schemas.</error>
</para>

<para>Alternatively, the <tag>cx:trang-files</tag> step operates directly on
files on the filesystem. For some conversions this may be easier than
constructing the correct set of source schema documents.</para>

<para>If a <option>source-format</option> option is not provided, the step will attempt to
determine the format by looking at the first input schema.
<error code="cxerr:XC0033">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the format
cannot be determined from the first schema.</error>
<error code="cxerr:XC0026">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if an XML Schema
is provided on the <port>source</port> port.</error>
<error code="cxerr:XC0034">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the document on
the source port is an XML document and it is not a RELAX NG Schema.</error></para>

<para><error code="cxerr:XC0036">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the source
and result formats are the same.</error>
</para>

<para>The converted schema documents are provided on the <port>result</port> port.
Each one will have a base URI that is resolved against the <option>output-base-uri</option>.
</para>

<para>Source and result parameters can be used to control the translations.
<error code="cxerr:XC0027">It is a <glossterm>dynamic error</glossterm> if the value
supplied for a parameter is not valid for that parameter.</error>
</para>

<refsection>
<title>Source parameters</title>

<para>The allowed source parameters vary depending on the source format.
Consult the Trang documentation for more details.
</para>

<refsection>
<title>DTD source parameters</title>

<para>The <option>namespaces</option> option specifies namespace bindings for
elements and attributes. They are prefix/URI pairs where the empty string
represents the default namespace.</para>

<para>The other source parameters are:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>colon-replacement</literal></term>
<listitem><para>Characters to use when replacing colons in DTD element and attribute names
to produce the name of a RELAX NG pattern.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>element-define</literal></term>
<listitem><para>A name pattern used to produce the name of a RELAX NG pattern
from an element name.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>inline-attlist</literal></term>
<listitem><para>If the inline-attlist parameter is true, the attribute declarations
will be part of the element pattern. If it’s false, they will be in their own pattern.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>attlist-define</literal></term>
<listitem><para>A name pattern used to produce the name of a RELAX NG pattern
from an attribute name.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>any-name</literal></term>
<listitem><para>Specifies the name of the definition generated for the content
of elements declared in the DTD as having a content model of ANY.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>strict-any</literal></term>
<listitem><para>If true, preserves the exact semantics of ANY content models by
using an explicit choice of references to all declared elements. If it’s false,
Trang uses a wildcard that allows any element.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>annotation-prefix</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The prefix to use for RELAX NG DTD Compatibility annotations. The 
default is “<literal>a</literal>”.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>generate-start</literal></term>
<listitem><para>If true, Trang will generate a start element.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>The encoding parameter is not supported for DTDs.</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>RELAX NG source parameters</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>encoding</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The input encoding.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsection>
</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Result parameters</title>

<para>Several parameters are common to all of the result formats.</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>encoding</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The output encoding.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>indent</literal></term>
<listitem><para>Indent by the specified number of spaces when nesting.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>lineLength</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The maximum line length. Must be a value between 20 and 1024.
(This parameter is “lineLength”, not “line-length”.)
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<refsection>
<title>XML Schema result parameters</title>

<para>Several additional result parameters are supported for XML Schema results.</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><literal>disable-abstract-elements</literal></term>
<listitem><para>If true, Trang won’t use abstract elements and substitution groups.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>any-process-contents</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The <code>processContents</code> value for “<literal>any</literal>” elements.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><literal>any-attribute-process-contents</literal></term>
<listitem><para>The <code>processContents</code> value for “<literal>anyAttribute</literal>” elements.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Consult the Trang documentation for more details.</para>

</refsection>
</refsection>

</refsection>
</refentry>
